<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Spiel des Jahres 2023 on Analysis Paralysis</title>
    <link>https://recommend-games.github.io/tags/spiel-des-jahres-2023/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Spiel des Jahres 2023 on Analysis Paralysis</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <managingEditor>contact@recommend.games (Recommend.Games)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>contact@recommend.games (Recommend.Games)</webMaster>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 31 Jul 2023 16:25:13 +0300</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://recommend-games.github.io/tags/spiel-des-jahres-2023/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Spiel des Jahres 2023 winners</title>
      <link>https://recommend-games.github.io/posts/spiel-des-jahres-2023-winners/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Jul 2023 16:25:13 +0300</pubDate>
      <author>contact@recommend.games (Recommend.Games)</author>
      <guid>https://recommend-games.github.io/posts/spiel-des-jahres-2023-winners/</guid>
      <description>The cat&amp;rsquo;s out of the bag and the winners have been announced!
This year&amp;rsquo;s show was… long… On the one hand, it&amp;rsquo;s nice to have all three awards (including the Kinderspiel) back together in one announcement, but on the other hand, once you add special awards, the review of the 1983 awards, interviews etc, even die hard fans (and obviously I&amp;rsquo;m one of them) have a hard time keeping their attention up.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spiel des Jahres 2023 predictions – Part 2!</title>
      <link>https://recommend-games.github.io/posts/spiel-des-jahres-2023-predictions-part-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jul 2023 15:32:50 +0300</pubDate>
      <author>contact@recommend.games (Recommend.Games)</author>
      <guid>https://recommend-games.github.io/posts/spiel-des-jahres-2023-predictions-part-2/</guid>
      <description>The waiting is finally coming to an end! On Sunday, July 16, the jury will announce the winners of Spiel des Jahres and Kennerspiel des Jahres 2023. We&amp;rsquo;re blessed with another year of very strong games and I&amp;rsquo;m certainly very excited to learn what games will win the two awards.
After two years of calling both winners correctly, I&amp;rsquo;ve missed the Spiel des Jahres 2022 winner Cascadia last year, so I hope I&amp;rsquo;ll do better this year.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spiel des Jahres 2023 nominations</title>
      <link>https://recommend-games.github.io/posts/spiel-des-jahres-2023-nominations/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jul 2023 23:20:42 +0300</pubDate>
      <author>contact@recommend.games (Recommend.Games)</author>
      <guid>https://recommend-games.github.io/posts/spiel-des-jahres-2023-nominations/</guid>
      <description>Nominations are out! The jury selected a total of fifteen games for their longlist, ten for Spiel des Jahres and five for Kennerspiel des Jahres. Out of these games, three games each are nominated for the two awards and can hope to get the coveted meeple added to their covers on July 16.
Let&amp;rsquo;s dive straight into the nominations and recommendations, before we discuss how good (or bad) my predictions were and if the agreed with our Kennerspiel score.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spiel des Jahres 2023 predictions</title>
      <link>https://recommend-games.github.io/posts/spiel-des-jahres-2023-predictions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 May 2023 22:24:54 +0300</pubDate>
      <author>contact@recommend.games (Recommend.Games)</author>
      <guid>https://recommend-games.github.io/posts/spiel-des-jahres-2023-predictions/</guid>
      <description>Spiel des Jahres 2023 is around the corner! As in the previous years, I&amp;rsquo;ll try to predict what games have the best shot at ending up on the longlist (aka recommendations) and the shortlist (aka nominations) when the jury announces their picks on May 22nd.
As every year, I&amp;rsquo;ll let the algorithms speak. The predictions for the longlist come directly from the recommendendations out of all eligible1 games. Our very own Kennerspiel score is then used to sort those into their respective list of the top 10 contenders for either award.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
