<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Game of the Year on Analysis Paralysis</title>
    <link>https://recommend-games.github.io/tags/game-of-the-year/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Game of the Year on Analysis Paralysis</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <managingEditor>contact@recommend.games (Recommend.Games)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>contact@recommend.games (Recommend.Games)</webMaster>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2020 14:42:00 +0300</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://recommend-games.github.io/tags/game-of-the-year/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>And the Spiel des Jahres 2020 goes to… Part 4!</title>
      <link>https://recommend-games.github.io/posts/and-the-spiel-des-jahres-2020-goes-to-part-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2020 14:42:00 +0300</pubDate>
      <author>contact@recommend.games (Recommend.Games)</author>
      <guid>https://recommend-games.github.io/posts/and-the-spiel-des-jahres-2020-goes-to-part-4/</guid>
      <description>After months of waiting, we finally know what games won this year&amp;rsquo;s Spiel des Jahres and Kennerspiel des Jahres! Without further ado, I&amp;rsquo;ll present the winners along with a comment on how the predictions went.
Spiel des Jahres 2020 Pictures Reading through the comments on the interweb most players seem surprised about the winner of the red meeple. Not me! It was on my list from the very beginning as probably the strongest contender.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>And the Spiel des Jahres 2020 goes to… Part 3!</title>
      <link>https://recommend-games.github.io/posts/and-the-spiel-des-jahres-2020-goes-to-part-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jul 2020 10:15:00 +0300</pubDate>
      <author>contact@recommend.games (Recommend.Games)</author>
      <guid>https://recommend-games.github.io/posts/and-the-spiel-des-jahres-2020-goes-to-part-3/</guid>
      <description>Spiel des Jahres and Kennerspiel des Jahres winners are due to be announced on Monday, July 20. I promised last time I&amp;rsquo;d be back with more detailed analyses and predictions. So here we go!
Out of hundreds of games published in 2019 and 2020, the jury selected a total of fifteen games they recommend, six of which they nominated for the two main awards. But who is the favourite? Who is the dark horse?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>And the Spiel des Jahres 2020 goes to… Part 2!</title>
      <link>https://recommend-games.github.io/posts/and-the-spiel-des-jahres-2020-goes-to-part-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 May 2020 18:31:00 +0300</pubDate>
      <author>contact@recommend.games (Recommend.Games)</author>
      <guid>https://recommend-games.github.io/posts/and-the-spiel-des-jahres-2020-goes-to-part-2/</guid>
      <description>With Spiel des Jahres and Kennerspiel des Jahres nominations out (setting aside the Kinderspiel again), it&amp;rsquo;s time to look at the nominees and to check how I did in my predictions.
Nominated for Spiel des Jahres As every year, the jury nominated three games for the main award, one of which will receive the red meeple in July. In addition to that, there are six games the jury recommends. Do these games match the criteria I stipulated last time?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>And the Spiel des Jahres 2020 goes to…</title>
      <link>https://recommend-games.github.io/posts/and-the-spiel-des-jahres-2020-goes-to/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 May 2020 15:35:00 +0300</pubDate>
      <author>contact@recommend.games (Recommend.Games)</author>
      <guid>https://recommend-games.github.io/posts/and-the-spiel-des-jahres-2020-goes-to/</guid>
      <description>For the impatient: If you don&amp;rsquo;t care about the analysis of previous winners and all you&amp;rsquo;re interested in are the candidates for this year&amp;rsquo;s awards, jump straight to the list…
It&amp;rsquo;s that time of year again when the whole board game scene takes a deep look into their crystal balls: On Monday, May 18, the jury Spiel des Jahres will announce the nominees for the game of the year award in Germany.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
