<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Kennerspiel des Jahres 2021 nominations on Analysis Paralysis</title>
    <link>https://recommend-games.github.io/tags/kennerspiel-des-jahres-2021-nominations/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Kennerspiel des Jahres 2021 nominations on Analysis Paralysis</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <managingEditor>contact@recommend.games (Recommend.Games)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>contact@recommend.games (Recommend.Games)</webMaster>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 May 2022 22:00:00 +0300</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://recommend-games.github.io/tags/kennerspiel-des-jahres-2021-nominations/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Spiel des Jahres 2022 nominations</title>
      <link>https://recommend-games.github.io/posts/spiel-des-jahres-2022-nominations/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 May 2022 22:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
      <author>contact@recommend.games (Recommend.Games)</author>
      <guid>https://recommend-games.github.io/posts/spiel-des-jahres-2022-nominations/</guid>
      <description>Nominations are out! The jury selected a total of fifteen games for their longlist, nine for Spiel des Jahres and six for Kennerspiel des Jahres. Out of these games, three games each are nominated for both awards and can hope to get the coveted meeple added to their covers on July 16.
Let&amp;rsquo;s dive straight into the nominations and recommendations, before we discuss how good (or bad) my predictions were and if the agreed with our Kennerspiel score.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spiel des Jahres 2021 predictions – Part 2!</title>
      <link>https://recommend-games.github.io/posts/spiel-des-jahres-2021-predictions-part-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
      <author>contact@recommend.games (Recommend.Games)</author>
      <guid>https://recommend-games.github.io/posts/spiel-des-jahres-2021-predictions-part-2/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s time! On Monday, July 19, we will finally know which games won Spiel des Jahres and Kennerspiel des Jahres 2021. I really think this is an exciting year with six very strong nominees that all have a lot of arguments going for themselves (and a few against). Even after following the whole year releases very closely, I&amp;rsquo;m still torn as to who&amp;rsquo;d be the favourites to win. Algorithms won&amp;rsquo;t be much help here either – the sample is just too small.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spiel des Jahres 2021 nominations</title>
      <link>https://recommend-games.github.io/posts/spiel-des-jahres-2021-nominations/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 May 2021 23:25:00 +0300</pubDate>
      <author>contact@recommend.games (Recommend.Games)</author>
      <guid>https://recommend-games.github.io/posts/spiel-des-jahres-2021-nominations/</guid>
      <description>Nominations are out! The jury selected a total of fifteen games for their longlist, eight for Spiel des Jahres and seven for Kennerspiel des Jahres. Out of these games, three games each are nominated for both awards and can hope to get the coveted meeple added to their covers on July 19.
Let&amp;rsquo;s dive straight into the nominations and recommendations, before we discuss how good (or bad) my predictions were and if the Kennerspiel score is any good.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
