<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Pages on Analysis Paralysis</title>
    <link>https://recommend-games.github.io/page/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Pages on Analysis Paralysis</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <managingEditor>contact@recommend.games (Recommend.Games)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>contact@recommend.games (Recommend.Games)</webMaster>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 26 Apr 2020 12:00:00 +0300</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://recommend-games.github.io/page/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://recommend-games.github.io/page/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Apr 2020 12:00:00 +0300</pubDate><author>contact@recommend.games (Recommend.Games)</author>
      <guid>https://recommend-games.github.io/page/about/</guid>
      <description>Recommend.Games Recommend.Games strives to recommend the best board games for you. We take the user ratings from BoardGameGeek (BGG), apply some black magic, and present recommendations that suit you. Check out its own About page to learn more about the details!&#xA;If you enjoy our work, please check out the Donations page or tell your friends about us.&#xA;Analysis Paralysis This blog takes the data we collect for Recommend.Games and tries to answer insteresting questions with them (at least we think they are interesting).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Donations</title>
      <link>https://recommend-games.github.io/page/donations/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Apr 2020 12:00:00 +0300</pubDate><author>contact@recommend.games (Recommend.Games)</author>
      <guid>https://recommend-games.github.io/page/donations/</guid>
      <description>Recommend.Games and Analysis Paralysis always have been and always will be 100% open source and free from paywalls, ads or tracking. If you find some value in what we&amp;rsquo;re doing and your finances allow you to support us with server costs etc, you can do so by donating through any of the links below (Wise and PayPal allow us to keep most of your donation):&#xA;Wise PayPal Patreon Ko-fi Liberapay GitHub sponsors If you&amp;rsquo;d rather donate to a charity of your choice, why not give some money to an organisation that promotes a more diverse, sustainable and loving world on our behalf?</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
